<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homes on Stephanie L. Johnson</title>
    <link>http://stephlj.github.io/home/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homes on Stephanie L. Johnson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019, 2020 Stephanie Johnson</copyright><atom:link href="http://stephlj.github.io/home/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/home/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/home/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a scientist with a broad, interdisciplinary background encompassing experimental biophysics, quantitative biochemistry, microscopy, and computation. I am currently developing software tools and a data science program for live cell, single molecule microscopy-based drug discovery at Eikon Therapeutics.
I received my Ph.D. from the California Institute of Technology in 2012 with Rob Phillips, where I used a brightfield microscopy assay, along with theoretical modeling, to make precise measurements of sequence-dependent DNA flexibility and its role in bacterial transcriptional regulation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/home/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/home/publications/</guid>
      <description>Johnson S.L., Narlikar G.J. (2020) ATP hydrolysis coordinates the activities of two motors in a dimeric chromatin remodeling enzyme. bioRxiv.
Armache J.P.*, Gamarra N.*, Johnson S.L., Leonard J.D., Wu S., Narlikar G.J., and Cheng Y. (2019) Electron cryo-microscopy structure of remodeler-nucleosome intermediates suggest allosteric control through the nucleosome. eLIFE 8: e46057. (*equal contribution)
Gebala M., Johnson S.L., Narlikar G.J., and Herschlag D. (2019) Ion counting demonstrates a high electrostatic potential of the nucleosome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/home/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/home/cv/</guid>
      <description>Long-form CV (pdf) Professional Experience 2020 - present Eikon Therapeutics Software Engineer
2019 Adecco for Google Research Scientist Consultant Worked with the Google Accelerated Science team to produce breakthroughs in the natural sciences by applying Google technologies.
Education/training 2013 - 2019
University of California, San Francisco
Postdoctoral fellow in Biochemistry and Biophysics
Mechanistic dissection of ATP-dependent chromatin remodeling motors using a combined ensemble biochemistry and single-molecule biophysics approach.
Advisor: Geeta Narlikar</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code</title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/home/code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/home/code/</guid>
      <description>Traces, single-molecule FRET analysis code
Slopey, for the quantification of single-molecule FRET trajectories containing fast, non-instantaneous transitions (see these slides for an introduction to Slopey and its application to the analysis of a chromatin remodeler&amp;rsquo;s reaction mechanism)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials</title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/home/tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/home/tutorials/</guid>
      <description>Histograms vs CDFs, on the uses of histograms, KDEs, and CDFs for cluster analysis
Are my data exponentially distributed?, on how to determine underlying distributions that your data could be drawn from
Bootstrapped error calculations, on estimating errors based on a bootstrapping method</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
