<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tutorials on Stephanie L. Johnson</title>
    <link>http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tutorials on Stephanie L. Johnson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019, 2020 Stephanie Johnson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the differences between histograms, KDEs and CDFs</title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/histosvscdfs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/histosvscdfs/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt; Back to homepage
A question we often want to ask of single-molecule data is whether the data fall into one or more clusters. For example, perhaps we have a single-molecule FRET system in which each molecule we observe explores either two or three states. We might want to ask whether all of the molecules in a population explore the same three states, or if the molecules that explore only two states share either state with the three-state population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are my data exponentially distributed?</title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/exponentiality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/exponentiality/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt; Back to homepage
To first order approximation, the results of single molecule measurements of time-dependent processes in a biological system are usually exponentially distributed. This is because we are often measuring the time to an event that has some fixed, independent probability of occurring in any instant (where an instant means a short interval of time).
Think, for example, of radioactive decay: in each instant, an atom in the sample has some fixed probability of decaying (given that it hasn&amp;rsquo;t already decayed).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapped error calculations</title>
      <link>http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/bootstrapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://stephlj.github.io/tutorials/bootstrapping/</guid>
      <description>&amp;lt; Back to homepage
Bootstrapping is a well-established method for estimating statistical errors (rather than, say, systematic or technical errors). The idea behind the bootstrap is to ask how much the estimate of whatever you&amp;rsquo;re interested (e.g. the mean of your data) would have changed if you&amp;rsquo;d collected a slightly different set of data, but still drawn from the same underlying population distribution. If your estimate is being substantially influenced by an outlier or some other peculiarity not representative of the data set, the bootstrap can let you know.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
